This week, we've done a wide sweep through
some of the deepest aspects of learning.
Metaphors and analogies aren't just for
art and literature.
One of the best things you can do to not
only remember but more easily understand
concepts in many different fields is to
create a metaphor or analogy for them.
Often the more visual, the better.
We've learned from
Nobel Prize Winner Santiago Ramón y Cajal
that if you change your thoughts,
you can really truly change your life.
It seems people can enhance
the development of their neuronal circuits
by practicing thoughts
that use those neurons.
Like Santiago Ramon y Cajal,
you can take pride in aiming for
success because of the very things that
make other people say you can't do it.
Keep in mind that when you
whiz through a homework or
test question, and
you don't go back to check your work,
you're acting a little like a person who's
refusing to use parts of your brain.
You're not stopping to take a mental
breath, and then revisit what you've
done with the bigger picture in mind,
to see whether it makes sense.
Overconfidence in your results can result
from using only one mode of thinking.
By making it a point to do some
of your studying with friends,
you can more easily catch where
your thinking has gone astray.
Taking a test is serious business.
Just as fighter pilots and doctors go
through checklists before takeoff and
surgery, going through your own
test preparation checklist can
vastly improve your chances of success.
Counterintuitive strategies, such as
the hard start jump to easy technique,
can give your brain a chance to
reflect on harder challenges,
even as you are focusing on other,
more straightforward problems.
Here are some last test-taking pointers.
The body puts out chemicals
when it's under stress.
How you interpret your body's reaction to
those chemicals makes all the difference.
If you shift your thinking from,
this test has made me afraid, to,
this test has got me excited to do my
best, it helps improve your performance.
If you're panicked on a test, momentarily
turn your attention to your breathing.
Relax your stomach.
Place your hand on it, and
slowly draw a deep breath.
Your hand should move outward, and your
whole chest should expand like a barrel.
Your mind can trick you into thinking
that what you've done is correct,
even if it isn't.
This means that, whenever possible,
you should blink, shift your attention,
and then double-check your answers
using a big-picture perspective,
asking yourself,
does this really make sense?
And finally, remember that not
getting enough sleep the night
before a test can negate any
other preparation you've done.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for
learning about learning.